[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software this is Sam tager for SE radio
IET orog is the creator of a gamified
devops training tool called lean poker
she has over 15 years of experience in
software development and Leadership and
today we are going to talk about rewrite
versus refactor we've talked about
similar subjects on the podcast
previously in episode 615 tidy first 638
architecture modernization and 625
automated refactoring welcome Evette hi
so you have some unconventional views
around the refactor versus rewrite
debate before we get to that though how
do we get to this decision point where
we have to decide whether to rewrite or
refactor I think that one of the core
issues with software development is that
we tend to have these emergent systems
and as we develop them over time they
get so complex that we lose track of it
and it becomes really hard to maintain
and there are lot of ways we can avoid
that the problem is that those ways are
expensive and I think this is the
controversial part where I'm saying that
yes you can actually keep a system clean
enough that you can can always move fast
but that effort of keeping the code Base
clean is a nonzero effort which is too
expensive for small companies which
leads to the consequence of almost every
single successful company having a code
base that is considered Legacy or
considered something that most Engineers
don't really like touching yeah that was
going to be my next question so how does
this relate to the term Legacy code what
exactly does that mean to you
yeah so I really like the definition of
Michael feathers that any code that
doesn't have tests is leg code I feel
like it's not complete in the context of
his book that definition absolutely
makes sense but I have seen code bases
that had tests and were still really
hard to maintain or even add features to
so I think that a better way of looking
at it is basically Legacy code is code
that I feel uncomfortable working with
and that is kind of a more general
definition for me also because like I
have seen code bases that didn't have
test and I was still comfortable working
in it yeah so can you dive into that a
little bit can you give some examples of
some code bases that had tests but were
hard to maintain yeah so the code base
that we struggled with was a PHP Legacy
code base and part of the reason it was
really hard to work with is because it
was started by a bunch of Junior
Engineers without any adult or oversight
so they basically ended up creating this
really hard to maintain codebase where
logic was intermixed with templating and
with database interactions and
everything and over time we started
adding tests to it but honestly like
when you have that level of complexity
just mixed up even adding those tests
can only help you so far right you still
need to refactor laot and sometimes even
if you do refactor you might end up with
like a system that is logically
insufficient in the sense of so the
specific example I want to give is an
import process that we had and that
import process was meant to process a
CSV file and then move all the data from
the CSV file into the database
unfortunately the way this was
implemented is to move everything field
by field not even line by line like
every single field update was a separate
SQL query with lots of round trips uh to
the database and solving that issue is a
bit more than refactoring right because
we do need to change the behavior of the
system and how do you do that without
actually rewriting the whole system that
was the question that we had to answer
in that case I would imagine the test
may have gotten in your way as well
because you'd have to rewrite the test
to change the system Behavior yes
luckily we didn't really have unit tests
I say luckily exactly because of the
reason what you said it would be really
hard to not break those unit tests while
you are doing something like this we had
more like endtoend tests and those were
a bit more reliable because we didn't
have to like it didn't touch the
internal logic of the system it was
actually just actually importing a CSV
file and then checking the database so
that was helpful but having said that we
did need to seriously rethink this
system and have a complete different
approach for loading that data into the
database you also mentioned that you've
encountered some code that did not have
tests but was easy to refactor what made
that easy to refactor so one system that
was fairly easy to refactor actually it
was a system that had a back end and a
front end and interestingly the front
end was horrible and really hard to work
with because it was just really quickly
it was actually my own system I wrote
over a few days because I had a deadline
coming up so I just rushed it all
together so the front end was really
hard to work with but the back end was
actually fairly clean and also didn't
have any tests and the reason it was
really easy to work with back end was
because even though it didn't have tests
I kind of had a dashboard as part of the
front end that showed everything so when
I reloaded that page I immedi mediately
to tell if every single part of the
system is working because that single
page was kind of a test of course it
required me to know what to expect on
that page right but it was enough for me
to have a basic level feedback that is
enough for me to work with okay another
term that gets thrown around is
technical debt how does Legacy code
relate to the term technical debt that's
a really interesting concept and I think
some people don't like this term because
it kind of implies that like has this
parallel with financial depth and
businesses are very happy to go into
depth right that's all we have with
Investments Investments are about going
into depth so business people are
usually very comfortable with that
concept and because of that it becomes a
conscious decision if we want to take on
that right and I think a lot of
Engineers don't like that because that
means that they can be pushed to take on
dep which they might not want to be
pushed into at the same time I think
it's still a really valid concept and
actually it's even better than final
shut up because think about the ver case
scenario which is actually the typical
case scenario for a startup you start
building something and it either works
or it flops you might have a project
that seems like a good idea on paper you
build it you ship it and then no one
uses it which one would you rather have
Financial depth or technical Dept
because Financial Dept you still have to
pay the technical Dept that's really
easy to pay at this point because you
can just delete the code right and now
your whole Dept is gone so as a startup
often taking on technical Dept in this
passion like making a conscious decision
of deferring architectural decisions to
later and deferring refactoring to later
is a smart decision as long as I'm still
trying to race towards a point where I
can validate my idea do you find that
some teams on intentionally take on
technical debt is that a thing I think
it is a thing and I think that what I
would definitely advocate for is being
smart about technical de right you don't
want to take it on unintentionally you
want to make a calculated decision when
you're taking on technical dep you need
to be aware that you can run into a
situation where you bankrupt yourself
because of technical ADT so a minute ago
I talked about being able to delete the
code and then the technical adopt is
gone that's true but at the same time if
your product is successful then you have
a different problem then you have
technical dep that you consciously or
unconsciously have taken on and now you
need to fix that because over time it
will become really really hard to get
out of it because it's oo exponential
just with normal monitor depth technical
depth can become an exponential burden
can you give some specific examples of
where you've seen that happen some of
the projects that I have worked on we
basically every single time got
ourselves out of that technical adapt
right but there were projects again
going back to the phb system that had
the import that was part of a larger
system and there the amount of technical
depth that was already around meant that
the tee couldn't deploy a new version of
the software for over a year and when
they did they had to roll it back again
and then another half a year went by
just fixing bugs not even adding new
features and they had to roll back again
so this level of technical depth is
already catastrophic right and if it
wasn't for two very talented Engineers
who later became by Bosses coming on
board and fixing that system or starting
to fix that system that company could
have gone bankrupt what are the biggest
challenges that companies face dealing
with Legacy code and Technical debt and
how does that differ based on the scale
of the organization I think that the
scale of the organization is very
important in this respect because if you
are a small organization you can't
really get enough technical ADT so that
it causes you a problem with any small
scale system you can always get out of
the hole You Dig yourself into in a
couple of weeks when it becomes
interesting is with large scale systems
where there are a lot of
interdependencies and more importantly a
lot of communication overhead between
teams and this is kind of leading on to
a slightly different topic which is the
topic of microservices because I feel
like part of the appeal of microservices
is that it's kind of an architectural
style that makes sure that all of your
subsystems remain below that threshold
where you can create a huge issue with
technical depth and each of your
subsystems can have some amount of depth
but you can always fix it and you can
always decide to replace one part of the
whole system with a droing replacement
unlike with a large monolith where
Everything You Touch Is going to move
everything else do you feel that
microservices addresses that problem
successfully if done well yes and that's
also something that's important when
people talk about microservices they
often talk about microservices as just a
way of having multiple services that are
somehow interconnected and I don't think
that's the right way to look at it in my
view and as far as I understand what
Dave Farley talks about in his view as
well that these systems are meant to be
decoupled and independent of each other
and the the boundaries between them
should be very well defined and minimal
you mentioned that as an organization
scales the problems change where is that
line is there a line is it when you
split to multiple teams or is there some
other line that generally demarcates
where you need to change your approach
yeah I mean I only so one company go
through this shift right most of the
companies that I work with were either
before the shift or after and I have
only one sample to tell to extrapolate
from so I feel like I can give you a
guess which is I think it's around about
50 Engineers where this becomes a
problem but of course it will depend on
the variety of factors what is the
design stamina hypothesis and how does
the graph change when considering reite
versus refactor oh yeah that's an really
interesting concept so this is coming
from Martin fer he had this hypothesis
where he says if we start with good
design that means that we are going to
start off slowly and then as we progress
because our design is good we speed up
exponentially right so once we have done
a bunch of work then we have all these
building blocks that we can build
together I've seen this described as a
graph can you describe the X and Y axis
just for people who haven't seen it yeah
okay so let's imagine this graph on the
x- axis you have the time that it took
you to implement the number of features
and on the y- axis the number of
features that you have implemented okay
so when we go through time what you
would see is as you add new features
this graph is slowly growing right and
the question is how fast is this graph
growing is it going to grow slow or fast
and the design s hypothesis stipulates
that if you do no design then over time
at the beginning you will really quickly
add features because you don't have to
worry about design you are just piling
on features onto a system and then over
time this is going to slow down because
you haven't done a good design so you
will have all this technical depth
slowing you down that's one option the
other option is you do good design and
at the beginning you don't even
Implement features or only Implement a
few features and as you progress this
good design that you have done up front
will slowly help you move faster and
then suddenly you are on a really steep
curve where you can add lots of features
in a small amount of time now the tricky
part is that this hypothesis says that
at the beginning doing design will
result in less features over time and
after a certain period which is the
design payoff line after that point the
design will pay off and you will move
much faster with design so that's design
some hypothesis note that this actually
only assumes two possible options you
either do a lot of design up front or
you do no design there is no mid the
ground here yet and also if I remember
correctly that exact point is
indeterminate at where the two graphs
pass right no one knows exact when one
passes the other yes that's definitely
true we might have a guess where it
crosses and if you ask Engineers a lot
of Engineers are going to give you very
different estimates on where that line
is yeah I've heard JB reinberger talk
about this and I believe he said
something like if you're before the line
then it makes sense to not do the design
and if you're after the line then it
makes sense to do the design but the
problem is no one knows exactly where
the line is and which side your
Project's going to fall on and oou if
your project fails you are almost
definitely going to be before the payoff
line but if it's successful you're
almost definitely going to go beyond
that line because if you are successful
you're are going to start adding more
features so the big question is when to
choose what and maybe is there a middle
ground great so let's move into the
rewrite versus refactor debate and maybe
we'll revisit that graph again can you
define rewrite and refactor and talk
about the difference between the to a
purchase rewrite would be something
where you just throw away all of the
code and you start over from zero and
reflector would imply that you change
the system incrementally with just
modifying the structure without changing
the behavior and basically in a classic
setting or this classic definition of
refractor implies that you're doing it
in so small steps and every step of the
way you have a working system so that's
something that you do continuously to
clean your code base where it becomes
interesting is that often people talk
about bigger factors where you need to
change a bunch of things together in
order to get to a more sustainable
design and how do you make sure that you
don't just start doing that reflector do
parts of it and then have to end up
living with a hybrid situation so when I
talk about big refractors I talk about
situations where doing part of the
refactoring job might actually
temporarily make things worse I've
always thought of refactoring as
limiting Risk by taking smaller steps
when you do these larger refactorings
are you then increasing the risk in a
sense yes you might be increasing the
risk at the same time I feel like if
this is done well and in a sustainable
way and we can talk about what that way
is this can be a good thing having said
that if you can avoid having to do a big
refactor you should like my general
opinion is that you shouldn't do a
rewrite or reflector unless you
absolutely have to and then the question
is when is it that you absolutely have
to and what do you do then yeah that is
going to be a question and we will
revisit that in a minute before that
though are rewrite and refractor the
only two options or is it possible to do
like a part partial rewrite or something
like that yes so when I say rewrite I
often think of partial rewrites and this
is also an interesting concept here that
you might be tempted to rewrite an
entire system but often when you think
about it there is one specific part of
the system that is bugging you or that
is the most painful for you and thinking
about okay how can I limit the impact
circle like again I said that don't
rewrite or don't do big refactor if you
can avoid it but if you can't avoid it
often you don't have to do it with the
whole system often it's mostly just one
part of the system so yes partial
rewrites are a thing all right let's go
back to that previous question how do
you know when you've ended up at the
point where you don't have a choice but
you have to do some large scale
refactoring or rewriting what are the
signs what can we look for okay for me
some examples that I can give one
example was this import that I
previously mentioned there was no option
of refactoring because the logic of how
we did the import was fundamentally
fluid you can't refractor it because
that wouldn't change the behavior we
actually needed to change the the
underlying behavior of the system and
then refactoring is out of the question
another very typical case of you can't
do a reflector is when the platform you
are building on is is not suitable
anymore so one example that I like
bringing here is there is this
presentation software called prei and
the problem prei had was they built
their whole system in action script and
action script was a really trendy thing
at the time but of course since then we
know that it basically got killed off
because of a bunch of security issues
and because iPhone and Apple in general
started to block it all together
so there there was no option of
refactoring because they just had to
move to a different platform and then
you cannot refector so an example that
might be perhaps switching from one
language to another or maybe moving from
like maybe a SQL database to a nosql
database or something like that that
would require a bunch of changes yes
there definitely options I would feel
that even with a like a database switch
is more likely to be like you can still
do certain database switches with
refactoring actually there is even a
wonderful book refactoring databas is
just about that so you can actually do
stuff like that but yes when you have a
fundamental change either in the
behavior of the system or the way it is
built that is necessary for you to
enable new business capabilities that's
when you need to rewrite instead of ref
Factor what other factors should
organizations consider when deciding
between rewrite and refactor the way I
would refas the question is what are the
fundamentally required features of a
large scale reflector or Rite because I
feel like that in general you want to
stay on the small scale refactor side
but when it becomes obvious that the
system is not your friend here and you
are slowing down I think that most of
the time when you consider something
like this rewrite or big refector thing
that usually has to do with a very
specific business need that we have and
when you do that I think there are two
very important things to consider the
first thing to consider is how can I
make sure that this project is
delivering customer value something that
the user can also feel this might be
something like enabling a new feature
that wouldn't be possible with the
existing system or making sure that more
customers can be reached because we are
opening up a new market or maybe the
only thing that the user notices is the
system is more responsive or easier to
use but in the end one of the two
important things that I usually ask
teams when they consider rewrite is how
is this Rite going to contribute to
customer value the other thing that is
important important to consider is can
we do this incrementally can we make
sure that it's not an All or Nothing
effort we don't want to be in a
situation where we start a rewrite and
then we have to stop it and then
suddenly we have a half finished product
and we never get to release it right so
can we do this Rite in a way that parts
of the rewrite are already used and
enjoyed by customer
before we finish you don't believe in
burning the ships the old analogy of
like Sly across the sea and then like we
burn the ships so we know we're not
going back yeah not really not really
that's kind of either it comes to
software engineering or politics I don't
believe in revolutions I believe in
incremental improvements when we talk
about incremental what size increments
are we talking we're talking really
small increments how large do those
increments become before they get too
large I was say make it as small as you
can and at a minimum you should be able
to have a releasable and valuable
increment every two weeks if that
doesn't go maybe once a month but don't
go about once a month if you are above
that line you're very likely to run into
situations where you need to change
direction before you you actually can
release
something but having said that the
smaller the better I had thems who could
release every 3 days and that's the best
because then every 3 days you have a
validation that you are still in the
right direction every 3 days you get to
realize if you are in not in the right
direction and change direction so that's
for me the idle is as small as possible
I'm forming an analogy in my head I want
to if it resonates but I think of it as
like you're in a pond and you're like
hopping from liip pad to Lad so you're
like going from like one safe area
jumping to the next one or maybe my kid
really likes the floor is lava and you
jump from like one couch to another or
something and there's like all this
floating lava that you're trying to
avoid does that seem like a adquate
analogy of like trying to take those
Tiny Steps just to get to the next safe
spot I think that's a wonderful analogy
I haven't heard that before and I think
I'm going to steal this because it's it
really visually gives a good example of
of what we are talking about like the
larger you need to jump the more likely
you're are going to break your leg
that's very obvious thank you for this
anology yeah at least in the software
World though as you said if you take a
small a jump and you miss you can always
roll back which Flo lava maybe not if
it's actually real lava yeah yeah
definitely but you still get wet when
you fall into the water right so maybe
that lilypad example is even better
where yes I mean you can fall into the
water and it's not the end of the world
but the larger the distance the more
time you need to swim to the next lily
pad and it's going to be painful and
then you get out and you're wet and
you're cold not pleasant there's a lot
of Dogma out there that says don't ever
do a rewrite where did that come from
yeah I think that mainly comes from a
lot of companies failing with rewrites
right honestly I'm lucky enough that
every time I tried my hand at the reite
I was successful but that's probably
partly because my first reite was under
the guidance of someone who was really
good at this so I immediately learned
from the best how to do this well but
before like if you look back in more in
the history of software engineering
there were a lot of companies that
failed and there is an argument that
part of the reason ncape failed was
their attempt at rewriting Netscape
Navigator there were other factors there
that Microsoft actually got sued over
but one of the reasons was definitely
that they didn't deliver new features
for a long time and they basically LED
themselves fall behind the competition
why is the idea that we shouldn't
rewrite problematic have you seen any
examples of companies who put off
rewriting and it ended poorly as I said
there are certain situations where it's
inevitable to rewrite and I think what
can happen is this was actually a
project that I was involved in we kind
of had this situation where the product
manager would come with problems to us
and we would tell the product manager
yeah we cannot do this because of the
system is built like that and that's
getting in our way and then we explained
that for that to be possible we need
this amount of time and we did this a
couple of times and after like the 10
feature that we couldn't Implement uh
the product manager was obviously very
aggravated and was like come on we need
to build something you can't say for
everything that it's impossible to build
it and I think that was our signal that
it was time for rewrite or in that case
it was more of a continuous and smart
effort to refactoring but the point is
that if your
leadership is B into this concept of we
are not going to rewrite ever we are not
going to invest into rewriting you might
end up with a situation where your team
is not really able to deliver anything
new for a long time and as long as you
are willing to challenge the idea of
let's not do a big rewrite in a
situation like that I think it's okay it
just becomes problematic when you see
this effect of a system that is already
hard to maintain and you still stick to
this Dogma let's revisit the two factors
that you found that separate successful
wres from unsuccessful ones and the
first one was to make sure we deliver
customer value how do you measure
customer value well the easiest is if
you can build a feature that is kind of
an addon that people can buy separately
right that's the easiest because then
you have an actual monitor value on that
new feature a bit less comfortable one
or less obvious one is adaption rate so
one of the things that I really like
measuring when building anything new is
how many of our customers are actively
using the new feature because that
implies if it was a useful thing for
them or not and if something is useful
people are more likely to keep buying it
or recommend it to other people this
reminds me of something I saw a post of
yours on LinkedIn today I think that
said something along the lines of
observability is better than testing if
you have to choose is that related to
this because I would imagine that you
have to have observability in order to
know that the customers are actually
getting value is that making sense yes
this was actually a short that I
recently released and it was recorded at
one of my events at a Loker and this
context is very important to understand
what I'm talking about there because in
Lim poer people have their own little BS
are playing playing poker and they are
trying to beat each other but they are
playing continuously as they are
developing and one thing that happens
very often is that teams don't realize
that their bot is failing and then they
keep going on and losing points because
they haven't noticed the problem right
and what I learned during these events
together with people who came to these
events is that the best way to stop that
kind of situation is to have monitoring
and testing is important but often you
can omit test especially in smaller
systems you can omit the test and rely
more heavily on monitoring and ideally
not monitoring Twitter if people are
tagging your company in complaining
messages but more like looking at
failure rates looking at adoption rate
of different features stuff like this
and this really carries over well into
large scale software development because
what's common between Lim poer and large
scale software development is that you
don't really have a direct connection to
all of the customers you might have a
connection to a few customers but you
don't have a an overarching view the
only way you can get the overarching
view is from the customers and reality
is often a lot more complex than you
expect so you can write a bunch of tests
you can have a system that is locked
down regarding Its Behavior to the last
if statement right but if what you came
up with isn't performant or isn't
serving the customer or the customer is
finding ways to break that system the
only way you are going to know that is
from monitoring and especially in the
first phase of development when you're
are exploring what needs to be built
testing can even be a bit in your way
because you might need to change
existing tests over and over again
because your behavior is changing but
with monitoring you have a bit more
flexibility and also it actually
reflects on reality and every piece of
reality even the things that you don't
expect I imagine observability is a
large Topic in and of itself yeah
definitely I do remember seeing several
episodes on software engineering radio
about that I will see if I can find some
and put them in the show notes the last
question I have around the two factors
that you found both the making sure you
deliver customer value and doing things
incrementally are they both necessary do
you just need one or do you need both in
order to succeed the way I see it is if
you have both that's going to be a
project that is usually successful
having said that if you have Neer you're
almost definitely going to fail with no
customer value and an All or Nothing
project no sensible CEO or CTO will
stand behind that project right and then
the question is like if you can let go
of either of the two which one is more
likely that you can let go of and I
would say that if you don't have a clear
customer value but you still have a
clear business value you might still be
able to make it work but then you have
to be very diligent about making sure
that that business value is clear
obvious and that there is an incremental
progress letting go of the incremental
progress I think that's very unlikely to
ever fly because you would have to trust
your gut for too long I think that would
go towards risk taking larger steps
would make it more risky which would
then make the business people a little
bit more reluctant I think to endorse
that project and it seems like that
everything we talk about today is about
risk isn't it the risk of rewriting the
risk bigger factors the risk of going
for a long time without new business
value I guess yes it's all about risk
speaking of business value how do you
convince management that you're at that
point where something needs to be re
written or refactored and how do you
sell that rewriting or refactoring to
management that's an interesting
question this discussion is very much
based on the talk that I have and the
title there is how do you sell big
refactor right and here is the
interesting point you might not need to
it might not be the right approach to
try and Comm this business what it's a
much better approach is thinking about
okay what is the value the business
business needs right now and how can I
deliver that value while improving on my
systems architecture and if you come at
it from this direction then you don't
really have to convince the business
about the refractor you are convincing
the business that the thing that they
want you to build can be built the way
you are planning to build and depending
on your specific situation you might be
in a situation where you don't have to
share that you are going to do a rewrite
as part of this and in some situations
it might make more sense to share this
information it also depends on how
technical your leaders are right so I
would say there is a lot of nuance to
when to actually even share this
information but even if you share the
point is to make sure that you focus on
the business value that is being
delivered and only treat the re right as
an implementation datail if I understand
you correctly then the advice would be
to air on the side of not sharing if you
don't need to I wouldn't say that that
way I'm very much the kind of person who
prefers sharing and yeah I mean I I
usually have a really hard time not
sharing these kinds of informations well
I guess is there a difference between
sharing and asking permission right is
it like I'm going to do this rewrite or
refactor versus I'd like permission to
do this rewrite or refactor is that a
different conversation I think it's a
very different conversation so so maybe
let's phrase it like this never ask for
permission always focus on the business
value and share the decision your
decision to do a particular Rite or
reflector as an implementation detail
and then when it comes to deciding
whether this implementation detail is
relevant for your leader for
are they technical enough to need to
know this is this something that you
need their input on like are you taking
on a bigger risk again risk comes back
are you taking on a bigger risk with
this reite than what you're are
comfortable taking on your own without
informing them these are all aspects in
usually I would share a very high level
note about this implementation data
detail and dive deeper if they ask me to
dive deeper there is a leadership book
written by a guy from the Navy called
turn the ship Around by David Marquette
I don't know if you've read that book it
it's pretty popular over here in the US
and one of the things that he talks
about is having people underneath him
come to him and not ask permission to do
things but rather say this is what I
intend to do and I think that's might be
a good model here to go to your boss and
say I intend to rewrite this project or
refactor this project here's why and
here's the value to the customer to tie
this back to your two points because I
think they help sell the vision so
here's the customer value and here's how
we limit Risk by doing it incrementally
does that sound like a good way to
approach that yes I haven't read the
book turn brown I heard about it a lot
and now you make me want to read it but
yes that's very good approach of what
you said there do you have any examples
of people selling projects management
where they've succeeded or failed well
can most most L come from my own
experience I think I've succeeded every
single time once I got to the point
where I could very clearly phrase the
business value and very clearly show
Once I know how to mitigate the risk
right and part of it like this is what
we will see I can be very clear about
this is what we will see if I'm right
and this is how fast we can move this is
where I can get in a week or two and
then we will see the impact already and
if I can do that I think I have never
been in a situation where I couldn't
convince my leaders even if at the first
like sometimes their first answer might
be hey okay let's try this for two
sprints let's see how far you get and
then we we will decide for real right
this might be a a sensible approach from
leadership but I think that's a very
solid framework for convincing them it
would seem like your answer there also
involves the observability that we
talked about earlier because you're
setting up goals to observe your
progress right so you would have you
have like clear metrics or something of
like if we do this customer adoption
should change by X amounts or something
like that yeah and one of the things
that going back to that example of the
slow import process there we had a very
clear metric because how did we do that
we simply took one customer that had a
problem with that import their daily
import took 20 2 hours that doesn't fit
the day so that's an urgent problem
right there was already that urgency and
I could promise my leaders to deliver a
first version that only solves this
problem for that specific customer
within two weeks and we will be able to
measure the difference in speed for the
import and then we did that we went away
actually to four weeks not two weeks and
I originally planned but after four
weeks we had it released and the
difference was stly from 25 hours that
import got down to 5 Seconds like
imagine the difference 25 hours against
5 Seconds now that was a really clear
business value right and there was no
question about continuing this project
so that brings me to another question
have you ever abandoned a rate refractor
in the middle and what happens then and
how do you recover from that o that's
nice because again the simple project
seems to come up a lot because with that
project we then decided to move on and
we took other customers and we tried to
make sure that every single incremental
change that we do unlocks this new
import for a bunch of new customers we
went on this quest of implementing
features one by one and after about I
think it was like 4 months we got to the
point where like 98% of our customers
had the new import and only 2% had very
specific settings that couldn't be done
with the new import and that that point
the business decided yeah let's cut this
project we are going to do something
else and what a consequence here we had
to import processes now because this was
a rewrite and every customers that that
couldn't be moved to the new new import
had to work with the old import so we
had two systems that to each other and
that stayed around for another year
what's the consequence next time we had
to implement something new to this
import suddenly we had a technical depth
of having that few customers with the
old system turns out in the meantime we
lost half of those customers for other
reasons and suddenly we only had to
implement a few more features to
complete the Rite and then we could
delete the O import so the moral of the
story here is that it might not be a big
issue if you have a half finish dite in
this sense because you have two working
systems as long as those two working
systems don't Collide you are fine and
when they do then you will have a good
business case to finish the right I'm
just thinking of some rewrites that I've
seen that have failed and usually it end
up when they had two big systems Side by
and they were trying to I think part of
it was probably not adding enough value
on the new system to drive adoption of
it but the new one hadn't quite got the
adoption that they wanted and then they
end up maintaining two systems and that
just got very painful because the new
system was always playing catchup with
the old system and they're always trying
to add new features and the new features
then would need to go into both and have
you seen that type of scenario and do
you have any advice for that or avoiding
that definitely and here's the thing
like the key term that he used there was
playing ketchup if you're in a situation
where your new system needs to play
catchup that's a problem because then
you are not really incremental what I
mean by incremental is the new system is
taking load off the old system and we
are continuously moving customers or
processes over to the new system and
whenever we need to implement a new
thing we should be able to implement it
in the new system and without touching
the old system idly sometimes of course
you will have a situation where you have
to add in both places but the the point
that I want to make is that unless you
are in a situation where yeah unless
these are small cases where you have to
implement both you are not doing it
right you need to have a Rite where
everything new is only added to the new
thing and not to the old one I feel like
a lot of times when people end up in
that situation is maybe because the new
system isn't either taking too long or
not getting the adoption that they need
and then there becomes this like
timeline issue where like the new
system's here but the old system hasn't
seen any updates in so long and they're
afraid of losing people so like oh we
better update the old system is there
like a timeline that you should try to
keep a rewrite a refactor under in order
to like avoid that situation yeah I mean
again if we have a risk of losing
customers because they are on the old
system I would again ask why are they
solely on the old system could it be
that the two systems are integrated in
well enough that it becomes transparent
for the user which system are they using
right and if that's the case then you
don't have that problem with our import
example the user didn't know that there
were two Imports because there was a
part of the system that would decide can
we handle this with the new one and if
yes we would handle it with the new one
if no then we would handle it in the old
one and if there was a new feature that
wasn't implemented in the old and we had
also an old feature that wasn't
implemented in the new one then we might
actually say on the UI that hey these
two features cannot be used together
sorry and then then it becomes a
discussion of do we implement this in
the new system is this customer
important enough so in general ideally
that that should be case now there are
of course situations like for example
the the presei rewrite where they had to
move from action script to to JavaScript
there was no option like to make this
transparent for the user this was
actually two different systems and there
you actually need to accept the fact
that you are going to lose customers
because you can't like they couldn't
evenu the same system they ended up
creating a new presentation software
that works slightly differently and has
slightly different features so there
they they have to accept that there will
be customers lost in the example I was
thinking of it was a desktop app and
they were changing languages actually so
that required two separate executables
and so that I think that was part of
their problem I wonder does having a web
app make that easier doing something
like the Strangler fig pattern where you
like run the two side by side and then
you slowly switch people over is that a
useful pattern yeah that's definitely
the true like my experience shows in
this regard I have always worked in web
systems and never on desktop apps so I'm
not sure I would have really good advice
for desktop apps having said that I
think the visual studio to vs code shift
of Microsoft is a good example of a
desktop app being Rewritten and I think
what was really interesting there is
that they consciously aimed at a
different market right so vs code was
designed for people who would never
consider visual studio and because it
was for a different Market it was
basically accepted that they will have
two systems for a long time and it took
years I'm not even sure if Vis studio is
still a thing probably it is I'm not
that deep into the Microsoft ecosystem
but the point is that when you have that
kind of rewrite where you are basically
creating a new software there the
business value should be opening up new
markets and accepting that the old
markets are going to be served by your
old product for a long time to come yeah
that is my understanding that Visual
Studio itself is going to keep going and
vs code is its own separate thing and
and like you said I think they were
targeting a separate Market in the case
that I was talking about earlier they
were actually trying to replace the old
one with the new one and they were not
targeting a new market so yeah I would
probably advise against that unless you
can make sure that the two systems are
integrated in a sense
so the key thing is that you're always
delivering a full featured app you're
either always delivering a full featured
app or you are delivering a different
app for a different market and if you
can do that then I think it's fairly
safe if you can't your mileage way mayor
ey like I I I don't want to make very
categorical statements here in this
particular case it did not work out very
well so it would have done well to heat
that advice but okay thank you very much
for talking to us thank you very much
for SE radio this is Sam tiger thank you
for
listening thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by it e software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE-R doet
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at seo. slack.com you
can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening